Tanya Cushman Reviewer Reviewer's Name
The human voice.
It's the instrument we all play.
It's the most powerful sound in the world, probably.
It's the only one that can start
a war or say, I love you.
And yet many people have
the experience that when they speak,
people don't listen to them.
Why is that?
How can we speak powerfully
to make change in the world?
What I'd like to suggest,
there are a number of habits
that we need to move away from.
I've assembled for your pleasure
here seven deadly sins of speaking.
I'm not pretending this is an exhaustive list,
but these seven, I think, are pretty large.
Habits that we can all fall into.
First, gossip.
Speaking ill of somebody who's not present.
Not a nice habit, and we know perfectly well
the person gossiping five minutes later
will be gossiping about us.
Second, judging.
We know people who are like this in conversation,
and it's very hard to listen to somebody
if you know that you're being judged
and found wanting at the same time.
Third, negativity.
You can fall into this.
My mother in the last years of her life
became very, very negative, and it's hard to listen.
I remember one day I said
to her, it's October the 1st today,
and she said, I know, isn't it dreadful?
Laughter
It's hard to listen when somebody's that angry.
It's hard to listen when somebody's that negative.
And another form of negativity, complaining.
Well, this is the national art of the UK.
It's our national sport.
We complain about the weather, about sport, about politics,
about everything, but actually complaining is viral misery.
It's not spreading sunshine and lightness in the world.
Excuses.
We've all met this guy.
Maybe we've all been this guy.
Some people have a blame-thrower.
They just pass it on to everybody else,
and don't take responsibility for their actions.
And again, hard to listen
to somebody who's being like that.
Penultimate, the sixth of
the seven, embroidery, exaggeration.
It demeans our language, actually, sometimes.
For example, if I see something that really is awesome,
what do I call it?
Laughter
And then, of course, this exaggeration becomes lying,
out and out lying, and we
don't want to listen to people
we know are lying to us.
And finally, dogmatism.
The confusion of facts with opinions.
When those two things get
conflated, you're listening into the wind.
You know, somebody is bombarding you with their opinions
as if they were true.
It's difficult to listen to that.
So here they are, seven deadly sins of speaking.
These are things I think we need to avoid.
But is there a positive way to think about this?
Yes, there is.
I'd like to suggest that
there are four really powerful cornerstones,
foundations that we can stand on, if we want to,
if we want our speech to be
powerful and to make change in the world.
Fortunately, these things spell a word.
The word is hail, and it
has a great definition as well.
I'm not talking about the
stuff that falls from the sky
and hits you on the head.
I'm talking about this definition, too.
Greet or acclaim enthusiastically, which is, I think,
how our words will be received
if we stand on these four things.
So what do they stand for?
See if you can guess.
The H, honesty, of course.
Being true in what you say.
Being straight and clear.
The A is authenticity.
Just being yourself.
A friend of mine described it
as standing in your own truth,
which I think is a lovely way to put it.
The I is integrity.
Being your word.
Actually doing what you say
and being somebody people can trust.
And the L is love.
I don't mean romantic love, but
I do mean wishing people well.
For two reasons.
First of all, I think absolute
honesty may not be what we want.
I mean, my goodness, you look ugly this morning.
Perhaps that's not necessary.
Tempered with love, of course, honesty is a great thing.
But also, if you're really wishing somebody well,
it's very hard to judge them at the same time.
I'm not even sure you
can do those two things simultaneously.
So hail.
Also, now that's what you say,
and it's like the old song.
It is what you say.
It's also the way that you say it.
You have an amazing toolbox.
This instrument is incredible.
And yet this is a toolbox
that very few people have ever opened.
I'd like to have a little
rummage in there with you now.
Just pull a few tools out that you
might like to take away and play with,
which will increase the power of your speaking.
Register, for example.
Now, falsetto register may not be
very useful most of the time.
But there's a register in between.
I'm not going to get very technical about
this for any of you who are voice coaches.
You can locate your voice, however.
So if I talk up here in
my nose, you can hear the difference.
If I go down here in my throat,
which is where most of us
speak from most of the time,
but if you want weight, you need
to go down here to the chest.
You hear the difference?
We vote for politicians with lower voices.
It's true.
Because we associate depth with power and with authority.
That's register.
And we have timbre.
It's the way your voice feels.
Again, the research shows that we
prefer voices which are rich, smooth, warm,
like hot chocolate.
Well, if that's not you, that's
not the end of the world.
Because you can train.
Go get a voice coach.
And there are amazing things you
can do with breathing, with posture,
with exercises to improve the timbre of your voice.
Then prosody. I love prosody.
This is the sing-song, the meta-language that
we use in order to impart meaning.
It's route one for meaning in conversation.
People who speak all on one note
are really quite hard to listen to
if they don't have any prosody.
That's where the word monotonic
comes from, or monotonous, monotone.
Also, we have repetitive prosody now coming in,
where every sentence ends as if it were a question.
When it's actually not a question, it's a statement.
And if you repeat that one over and over,
it's actually restricting your
ability to communicate through prosody,
which I think is a shame.
So let's try and break that habit.
Pace.
I can get very, very excited
by saying something really, really good.
I can do it really, really quickly.
Or I can slow right down to emphasize.
And at the end of that,
of course, is our old friend silence.
There's nothing wrong with a bit
of silence in a talk, is there?
We don't have to fill it with ums and ahs.
It can be very powerful.
Of course, pitch often goes
along with pace to indicate arousal,
but you can do it just with pitch.
Where did you leave my keys?
Slightly different meaning in those two deliveries.
And finally, volume.
I can get really excited by using volume.
Sorry about that if I startled anybody.
Or I can have you really
pay attention by getting very quiet.
Some people broadcast the whole time.
Try not to do that.
That's called sodcasting.
Imposing your sound on people
around you carelessly and inconsiderately.
Not nice.
Of course, where this all comes from,
most of all, is when you've
got something really important to do.
It might be standing on a stage
like this and giving a talk to people.
It might be proposing marriage, asking for
a raise, a wedding speech, whatever it is.
If it's really important, you owe it
to yourself to look at this toolbox
and the engine that it's going to work on.
And no engine works well without being warmed up.
Warm up your voice.
Actually, let me show you how to do that.
Would you all like to stand up for a moment?
I'm going to show you the six vocal warm-up exercises
that I do before every talk I ever do.
Any time you're going to
talk to anybody important, do these.
First, arms up.
Deep breath in and sigh out.
Like that.
One more time.
Very good.
Now we're going to warm up our lips.
And we're going to go bop,
bop, bop, bop, bop, bop, bop, bop.
Very good.
And now,
just like when you were a kid.
Now your lips should be coming alive.
We're going to do the tongue next with exaggerated
la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la.
Beautiful.
You're getting really good at this.
And then roll an R.
That's like champagne for the tongue.
Finally, and if I can only do
one, the pros call this the siren.
It's really good.
It starts with we and goes to or.
The we is high, the or is low.
So you go, weeeeee.
Or.
Weeeeee.
Fantastic.
Give yourselves a round of applause.
Take a seat.
Thank you.
Next time you speak, do those in advance.
Now, let me just put this in context to close.
This is a serious point here.
This is where we are now, right?
We speak not very well into people
who simply aren't listening in an environment that's
all about noise and bad acoustics.
I have talked about that
on this stage in different phases.
What would the world be like if we
were speaking powerfully to people who are not listening?
I mean, I think that's a very important thing.
I think that's a very important thing.
In an environment that's all about noise
and bad acoustics, I have talked about that
on this stage in different phases.
What would the world be like if we
were speaking powerfully to people who are listening consciously
in environments which were actually fit for
purpose, or to make that a bit larger?
What would the world be like if we
were creating sound consciously and consuming sound consciously
and designing all our environments consciously for sound?
That would be a world that does sound beautiful.
and one where understanding would be the norm.
And that is an idea worth spreading.
Thank you.